<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Four Short Stories: A Digital Edition</title>
            <author>
               <persName>Fanny Van de Grift Stevenson</persName>
            </author>
            <editor> R Pritzker </editor>
            <principal> A Lang </principal>
            <funder> Centre for Data, Culture, and Society: University of Edinburgh </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <ab><!-- unpublished manuscripts with permission of the Robert Louis Stevenson Museum in St. Helena, California--></ab>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>St. Helena, California</settlement>
                  <repository>Robert Louis Stevenson Museum</repository>
                  <idno>Scrapbook 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="ScribeA" scribeRef="FVS">Clear, cursive script</handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <div hand="#ScribeA">
            <head type="title">Borriballoo</head>
            <p>
               <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda Smith found herself in a very unpleasant
               position. How it happened is not part of this story, which opens with <persName
                  corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda hanging by the belt on a hook in a giant’s
               kitchen. </p>
            <p>The cook was heating water, and sharpening knives for the evident purpose of
               preparing <persName corresp="#belinda"/>the unhappy girl for the giant’s table,
               she was just in the act of studying <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda’s
               length and breadth with an eye to a dripping pan of the right proportions when
               the giant entered.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda could see nothing in her terror but a huge
               unshapely bulk of frightful aspect. Really, however, <persName corresp="#giant"
               />the giant possessed a jolly, big good-humoured stupid face. Jolly people are
               apt to be a little stupid.</p>
            <p><said>“No luck again, today.”</said> He said, as he came thumping in. <said>“A
               pretty dish to sit before the grand Borriballoo, one pitiful child with a
               spoonful of gravy; and too late today for any more hunting. Is she nice and
               plump?”</said> as he advanced toward the terrified Belinda.</p>
            <p><said>“Halloo! What’s this?!</said> Stooping to pick up a bit of paper that had
               dropped from <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda’s pocket. As he glanced over
               the note, which was only a wash bill from Belinda’s mother, who did
               clearstacking, his countenance changed; he sighed heavily, and repeated the name
               signed to the note several times in a sad and touching voice; then reached up
               and unhooked <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda whom he placed upon a table
               by his side.</p>
            <p><said>“What is your name, child?”</said> he asked, in a very different voice from
               that he had used when he entered. <persName corresp="#belinda"/>
               <said> “Belinda Smith, you say? Ah yes, that name I have heard before. It is
                  truly a sweet name. You would hardly believe now, that a bluff old fellow
                  like myself had ever been in love? I have. It was your mother child. Many
                  years ago she fell into my hands much as you have done; I had intended her
                  for company, but before long she had <pb/>somehow wound herself into my
                  affections, she implored me to carry her to her father. I did so. From that
                  day to this I have never beheld her. I know now that it would have been
                  better to have eaten her as I intended to do, for then she would have been
                  part of my own being forever. Now it is too late. Like you, she was very
                  plump,”</said> looking dreamily at <persName corresp="#belinda"
                  />Belinda.</p>
            <p><said>“I think, my dear, for the sake of old times, and the memories of my youth,
               I will have you served with my guests instead of to them. Come, I will call
               <persName corresp="#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog, my son to show you to the
               guest chamber. Try to rest and sleep well that your eyes may be as bright,
               and your cheeks as rosy as your mothers were when I first saw
               her.”</said></p>
            <p>Lallagagog came at his father’s call and escorted <persName corresp="#belinda"
            />Belinda to her room. He was a saucy awkward lout of a giant boy and disposed
               to be sulky at the change in the morrow’s bill of fare.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda was too tired to think of the strange
               things that had occurred, and begging <persName corresp="#lallagagog"
               />Lallagagog to reach a pillow for her from the immense bed, she lay down upon
               it and slept until daybreak. In the morning it was some time before she could
               recall her scattered senses enough to recollect her whereabouts; but <persName
                  corresp="#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog’s hoarse voice calling her to breakfast,
               warned her to be in haste. She dressed rapidly and stepped into the hall where
               <persName corresp="#giant"/>the giant was waiting for her. He led her into
               the breakfast room. A box had been placed upon a chair for her and the giant
               lifted her to her place. Her acutest fears now began to dissipate, and she ate
               her breakfast with a good appetite, and even <said>carried on a conversation
                  with the giant with some diplomacy, giving full accounts of all the members
                  of the Smith family</said> that she knew anything about, especially of those
               who had become famous or possessed much political influence, hoping that the <pb/>
               <persName corresp="#giant"/>giant might have some fear of incurring the enmity
               of so great and influential a race.</p>
            <p>The giant listened politely, and looked impressed by what she had said. Suddenly
               a bright idea seemed to strike him.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="#belinda"/><said who="#giant">“Belinda,”</said> said he
               kindly, <said who="#giant">“How old are you?</said></p>
            <p><said who="#belinda">“Fifteen.”</said></p>
            <p>“My grandmother was married at fifteen,” remarked <persName corresp="#giant"/>the
               giant.</p>
            <p>“Was she indeed?” said Belinda, not knowing what else to say.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="#belinda"/>“Belinda,” more kindly still, “How would you like
               to be married?”</p>
            <p>A horrible fear took possession of <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda. Perhaps
               he wished to marry her himself. He must be a widower, she had seen no woman,
               yet, about the house but the cook, and for all she knew, giants might, anyhow,
               have as many wives as old <ref
                  target="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Brigham-Young"
                  >Brigham.</ref></p>
            <p>“I—I don’t—know” faltered poor <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda, bursting
               into tears.</p>
            <p>“Tut, tut, Pshaw!” said <persName corresp="#giant"/>the giant in not so kind a
               voice as before. “I’m not going to eat you, what are you crying for?”</p>
            <p>The cry was swallowed instantly, as <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda made
               haste to answer “I never thought of such a thing, I assure you! What were you
               about to say, please?” with a sickly attempt to smile.</p>
            <p>“Only this,” said <persName corresp="#giant"/>the giant, “that I am going to have
               company today to dinner; a personnage of great importance;” his voice took a
               deeper tone. “His Highness the <persName corresp="#borriballoo"/>Grand
               Borriballoo! It is to be quite an affair as it is only a business interview he
               seeks. “I,” and he swelled with conscious pride, “am Confidential Matrimonial
               Adviser to his highness! Of course a personage of his rank could not take the
               trouble to choose a wife for himself. That is my affair.<pb/> I have been in
               much perplexity because I could not fix upon an eligible party, when it suddenly
               occurred to me, why not <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda? You are certainly
               of a good family, belonging to a long line of Smiths. And being a protegee of
               mine gives you standing. Indeed, I consider it a very suitable match on both
               sides. Now, my dear, just think this matter over. At four precisely I will come
               for your decision.” Bowing politely he left the room.</p>
            <p>Belinda was in a whirl of agitation. What a brilliant future was before her! The
               <persName corresp="#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo, might, to be sure, be as old
               and ugly as the giant himself: but the bliss of being “My Lady Borriballoo”
               covered any unpleasant suggestions that arose in her mind. An occasional thought
               of the red headed boy, who sat next to her at school, and to whom she had been
               engaged for the past three weeks came to her remembrance once or twice, but was
               soon forgotten. What chance had a red headed boy beside the grand <persName
                  corresp="#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda had one ugly habit of which I am loth to
               speak. She was very apt to put her thumb in her mouth when thinking. She did so
               upon this occasion, as she sat wrapped in her reflections, <persName
                  corresp="#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog, who had been drowning flies in the cream,
               and amusing himself in other kindred ways, now turned his attention to <persName
                  corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda, stepping up softly behind her, he placed one
               great hand upon her head, the other under her chin, and suddenly snapped her
               teeth together with a loud laugh.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog did a worse mischief than he had
               intended. His hands were so strong, and the little white teeth so sharp, that
               <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda was placed in the awkward predicament
               of having bitten off her own thumb.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog ran off and hid himself, and poor
               <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda retired, weeping, to her chamber to
               bind up her mutilated hand <pb/>and invent an excuse for not appearing at
               dinner; for she hardly liked to make her first appearance before the <persName
                  corresp="#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo with a red nose and swollen eyes, and a
               bandaged hand.</p>
            <p>She finally pleaded a headache, a feeling of uncertainty and insecurity prompting
               her not to complain of <persName corresp="#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog.</p>
            <p>When <persName corresp="#giant"/>the giant saw her woebegone face, he very
               readily excused her, saying that if such was her pleasure, he would make all
               necessary arrangements himself.</p>
            <p>Ambition and pride rose in <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda’s heart, she
               gave her full consent to the proposed marriage.</p>
            <p>In the evening, the giant said that the grand <persName corresp="#borriballoo"
            />Borriballoo was perfectly satisfied with the description and account given of
               the bride elect, and only desired that she should be allowed to remain in strict
               seclusion until the day of the ceremony, in accordance with the customs of his
               ancestors.</p>
            <p>Preparations for the wedding went on apace, and at length the day arrived. The
               great hall of <persName corresp="#giant"/>the giant’s mansion was decorated with
               the most elegant taste, and hundreds of brilliant lights flashed upon the jewels
               and rich dresses of the guests.</p>
            <p>At opposite ends of the hall were great doors. These were thrown open
               simultaneously. Through one entered the <persName corresp="#borriballoo"/>Grand
               Borriballoo leaning upon the arm of the priest, at the same moment that
               <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda supported by <persName
                  corresp="#giant"/>the giant appeared at the other. <persName
                     corresp="#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog followed bearing her train.</p>
            <p>All eyes were turned towards <persName corresp="#belinda"/>the bride; but she saw
               nothing but the <persName corresp="#borriballoo"/>Grand Borriballoo, whom she
               now met for the first time. His carriage was majestic, and at the same time of a
               very peculiar grace, caused doubtless by his having three legs, instead of the
               usual number. His glittering tail was so <pb/>long that as he stood in the
               centre of the room its extremity reached to the entrance where it was borne by
               five and twenty pages in gold and white. His heavy locks of ferns and field
               flowers fell to his waist. His eye, placed in the centre of his forehead, was
               large and lustrous and full. In short, the most fastidious person could have
               taken no exception to his personal appearance.</p>
            <p>A sudden hush and expectant thrill fell upon the vast assembly as the <persName
               corresp="#borriballoo"/>grand Borriballoo advanced towards <persName
                  corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda, tenderly took her hand, gazed long and
               earnestly into her face, and signed the priest to continue. Why will not the
               fates allow me to stop here, nor further follow this tale which so suddenly
               changes to a scene of gloom and horror.</p>
            <p>As <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda, blushing, raised her hand to receive
               the ring from the <persName corresp="#borriballoo"/>Royal Borriballoo, the
               priest gently said “Your right thumb, if you please; it is the law that only
               thus a grand <persName corresp="#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo may marry.</p>
            <p>Unconsciously <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda raised her maimed right
               hand.</p>
            <p>The priest shrank back with a cry of horror, and the <persName
               corresp="#borriballoo"/>Grand Borriballoo fell to the floor in a deathlike
               swoon.</p>
            <p>“Ah I shall burst with mortification!” Groaned <persName corresp="#giant"/>the
               giant, which he immediately did with a loud report.</p>
            <p>The guests fled in terror, some of them mortally wounded.</p>
            <p>The ring, which had dropped from the hand of the bridegroom rolled along the
               floor to the feet of <persName corresp="#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog, who shyly hid
               it in his mouth. It stuck in his windpipe. In the confusion caused by his
               father’s explosion he was unnoticed, and soon choked to death.</p>
            <p>The whole proceedings were so frightfully indecorous that <pb/>the priest fell
               into a rage, which was so deep that no ropes would reach him, where he remains
               to this day.</p>
            <p>The end of the <persName corresp="#borriballoo"/>grand Borriballoo was sad beyond
               belief. Knowing his union with <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda was now
               impossible, he fell into a low state, weeping incessantly, neglecting the
               affairs connected with his rank and office, which consequently fell into other
               hands about whom his old friends rallied.</p>
            <p>His society had become so wearisome to those about him that he was left alone
               more and more, so that when he had wept his eye out so one was aware of the
               piteous fact, and he wandered for days in a thick wood adjacent to the castle
               vainly seeking his way out. At last, glum and weary, suffering intolerably from
               thirst and hunger, he sunk upon the ground.</p>
            <p>“Ah <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda” moaned he, as he wiped the growing
               cavern where his eye had been, with his tail, “would I had never beheld thee!”
               In his <span ana="Stevenson_OgraphyV1.xml#grief"
                  corresp="Stevenson_OgraphyV1.xml#borriballoo"/>anguish he accidentally
               placed the end of his tail into his mouth; unconsciously, in his delirium,
               assailed by the pangs of hunger, he began devouring it, and absently ate himself
               up. No remains were ever found except a few tail scales that his stomach was
               unable to digest.</p>
            <p>As to <persName corresp="#belinda"/>Belinda, no one knows what became of her.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      
      <back>
         <div type="editorial">
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="narratorA">
               </person>
               <person xml:id="belinda">
                  <persName>Belinda Smith</persName>
                  <sex value="F"></sex>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>human</label>
                  </trait>
                  
               </person>
               <person xml:id="lallagagog">
                  <persName>Lallagagog</persName>
                  <sex value="M"></sex>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>giant</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="giant">
                  <persName>the Giant</persName>
                  <sex value="M"></sex>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>giant</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="borriballoo">
                  <persName>Grand Borriballoo</persName>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>humanoid creature</label>
                     <desc>flowers for hair, long glittering tail, three legs</desc>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Sheep</persName>
                  <sex value="F"></sex>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>Sheep</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Lamb</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>she-wolf</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <interpGrp type="charActs">
               <interp xml:id="grief">indicating a character's display of grief, sadness, loss.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="fear">indicating a character's display of fear, anger, terror, distress.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="joy">indicating a character's display of joy, happiness.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="unsure">indicating a character's display of uncertainty, mistrust, or confusion.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
            <interpGrp type="genre">
               <interp xml:id="gothic">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the Gothic genre.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="wonder">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the wonder tale genre.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>