<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Four Short Stories: A Digital Edition</title>
            <author>
               <persName>Fanny Van de Grift Stevenson</persName>
            </author>
            <editor> R Pritzker </editor>
            <principal> A Lang </principal>
            <funder> Centre for Data, Culture, and Society: University of Edinburgh </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <ab><!-- unpublished manuscripts with permission of the Robert Louis Stevenson Museum in St. Helena, California--></ab>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>St. Helena, California</settlement>
                  <repository>Robert Louis Stevenson Museum</repository>
                  <idno>Scrapbook 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="ScribeA" scribeRef="FVS">Clear, cursive script</handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>



   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <div hand="#ScribeA">

            <head type="title">The Hunchback</head>
            <p>A boy older than his appearance would indicate was sitting sullenly alone in the
               woods by the side of a stream. The water was clear and cool, flowers were blooming
               among the grass, the sky was blue, a gentle air was stirring. The day was heavenly, a
               calm and holy beauty pervaded all nature except the heart of this unfortunate
               boy.</p>
            <p>And yet he deserved some communication, for he seemed to be deformed. An elaborate
               contrivance of straps and buckles passed around his shoulders, which appeared to be
               hunched in a peculiar fashion. Years ago, when a lovely child with a face and temper
               like an angels his parents, worthy people, had discovered that there was something
               strange and unusual in his appearance totally unlike that of other children. They
               were decent folk, and nothing had happened in their family for many generations out
               of the usual course. All the men were straight and tall, married comely and excellent
               housewives, and reared large families of the most eminent respectability. In short,
               lived and died in the regular orthodox fashion. The distress and horror of all the
               relatives may be imagined when the unsightly protuberance was first noticed. The lad
               was pitied by his parents, and scoffed at by his brethren, all alike as two peas.</p>
            <p>The physicians of his native place said “Let the child alone; give him some active
               useful employment and trust to him. Don’t use too much force, for the boy is of more
               delicate clay than the rest, and must be managed carefully.” But the parents in their
               anxiety, the father being what is called a man handy with tools, had invented this
               cruel arrangement of straps and buckles which seemed to have cut into the very soul
               of the boy. He grew gloomy and despondent, dull at his books, and took no apparent
               pleasure in the society of others of his age. The burden seemed to grow with his
               years, to lie as heavily on his heart as on his shoulders. </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>This perfect summer day he had wandered off, as usual, by the banks of the little
               stream. His brother had gone further up where the water was deeper, and trout were
               said to be in the pools. At times their laughter came floating down so merry and
               infectious that a smile almost reached the lips of the dull boy who stood brooding
               over the water.</p>
            <p>The wind rose somewhat, shaking down the autumn leaves in a shower at his feet,
               brown, crimson and gold. The heavy eyes brightened at the sight with a sudden light,
               like distant lightning after a tropical day. A brown bird began singing over his head
               as it swung on a bough. Softly as first, then louder and stronger and fuller, such a
               wild joyous rollocking ron de lay that the boy felt his pulses quicking and his heart
               pounding with the harmony. The wind came stronger, with a breath of the sea. The song
               of the brown bird filled all the air. The boy stood upright, and with eager hands
               tore furiously at the ligatures that bound his shoulders. Buckles and straps parted
               and fell rattling to the ground. A very curious thing happened. Released from their
               bonds, two great wings of purple and gold quivered in the sunlight. A beauty not of
               the earth shone in the face of the boy, with a quick glance upward he thrust aside
               the overhanging leaves, pushed the air with his burnished wings and swept away
               towards the east. The brown bird looked up, ceased its song, and hid its head beneath
               its wing.</p>
            <p>The next day, flying over the marshes to meet its love, in a bare and desolate place
               it discerned a gleam of color. Swooping down to examine closer a thing so unusual it
               found the poor boy dead and cold in the slump of the marsh. The muscles of his wings
               for so many years unused to action had become flaccid and weak. In his elation at the
               discovering of his marvellous powers he had miscalculated his strength, attempted too
               high a flight, and thus failed miserably in this outset of his career, and so had
               died in the mire, the green ooze rising about his face and his purple wings trailing
               broken and soiled.</p>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="editorial">
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="narratorC"> </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>the Hunchback</persName>
                  <sex value="M"/>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>humanoid</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Mother</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Father</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <interpGrp type="charActs">
               <interp xml:id="grief">indicating a character's display of grief, sadness,
                  loss.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="fear">indicating a character's display of fear, anger, terror,
                  distress.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="joy">indicating a character's display of joy, happiness.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="unsure">indicating a character's display of uncertainty, mistrust, or
                  confusion.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
            <interpGrp type="genre">
               <interp xml:id="gothic">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the Gothic
                  genre.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="wonder">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the wonder tale
                  genre.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
