<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Four Short Stories: A Digital Edition</title>
            <author>
               <persName>Fanny Van de Grift Stevenson</persName>
            </author>
            <editor> R Pritzker </editor>
            <principal> A Lang </principal>
            <funder> Centre for Data, Culture, and Society: University of Edinburgh </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <ab><!-- unpublished manuscripts with permission of the Robert Louis Stevenson Museum in St. Helena, California--></ab>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>St. Helena, California</settlement>
                  <repository>Robert Louis Stevenson Museum</repository>
                  <idno>Scrapbook 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="ScribeA" scribeRef="FVS">Clear, cursive script</handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>


   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <div hand="#ScribeA">
            <head type="title">Easy Reading for an Old Bachelor, the Story of The Ravening
               Sheep</head>
            <p>A weak minded sheep and her lamb once lived on a bit of barren land; there were
               several small spots where clover grew, and a little shelter of old brush. They
               were not well cared for, but they made the best of what they had, and were
               reasonably happy. One day a she wolf brought over to their place, from her own
               green fields, several sheep from her flock; they devoured all the clover that
               was the only <subst>
                  <del rend="overstrike">subsistence</del>
                  <add place="supralinear">sustenance</add>
               </subst> of the sheep and lamb, and carelessly threw over their shelter of
               boughs.</p>
            <p>It sounds odd that a she-wolf should have charge of a flock; but this was a wily
               she- wolf; there were many wolves in the forest, and game was scarce and shy, so
               she got a place with a shepherd as a sheepdog. The shepherd was blind, and old,
               and foolish, and never knew the imposture. The neighbours, who were reluctant to
               meddle in other people’s affairs, did not like, or did not choose to tell him;
               so the she-wolf and her cubs waxed fast and strong, while her kinsmen of the
               forest, gaunt and hungry roamed <pb/> about, seeking their prey.</p>
            <p>It was not that she particularly wished to harm the sheep and lamb that the
               she-wolf robbed them, but that her natural instincts inclining her to a
               guerrilla life occasionally overcame the teachings of civilization.</p>
            <p>It was hard upon the sheep and the lamb. A cold rain fell, and winter was not far
               off. Before the clover had started to grow again, the shivering lamb was dead.
               The sheep tried to warm it with her own body, but her wool was wet, and she,
               too, was starved with the cold; she could only watch her lamb’s innocent eyes
               grey, and its little legs stiffen, with a breaking heart. She could do nothing;
               she could not replace the shelter, nor could she make the grass grow again,
               though she would gladly have watered the grass with her blood, and torn the
               fleece from her back to keep the cold from the lamb.</p>
            <p>When the lamb was dead it was thrown into a hole. <span
               ana="Stevenson_OgraphyV1.xml#grief" corresp="Stevenson_OgraphyV1.xml#sheep"
               >The sheep, in her grief, hoped and thought she might die too; but she was
               older and stronger and more used to hardship than the lamb, so, sad and
               lonely, she held on and endured the cold and the hunger. Most of the time
               she either stood gazing <pb/>at the hole where they had thrown her lamb, or
               wandered about the bare pasture where it had frisked and played in happier
               days. Once a cub of the she-wolf came that way; it was so plump, and sleek,
               and well cared for, that when the bereaved sheep looked upon it she felt her
               weak heart giving way because of the injustice of things, and in a mad rage
               chased the wolf-cub howling away to its mother.</span></p>
            <p>The next day the blind shepherd came in a great rage to the sheep. The wolf-cub
               had come panting home with a fearful tale; the sheep, she said, had come at her
               with a mouth a yard wide, full of blood and foam; with eyes the size of dinner
               plates, from which shot blue and green flames, and with an awful, deafening roar
               like a wild lion.</p>
            <p>The sheep could not remember these details, but full of trouble went off alone to
               think it over; and wondered if all this were really true, and she had actually
               become a mad ravening sheep.</p>
            <p>Soon she met the Haymaker who was fond of walking in paths and places where the
               shadows were heavy. He was called the Haymaker because he was supposed to make
               hay while the sun shone. All people went to him for advice, he was
               <pb/>accounted so very wise; he was thought to be wise because he had many
               books, and he looked solemn, and he often said “policy is better than honesty,”
               “don’t whistle too much for your pay,” and other things that showed a profound
               intellect, and a habit of deep thought. When he demanded the reason of the
               sheep’s depression of mind, she, being in awe of so great a man, told her
               story.</p>
            <p>“I must tell you what to do,” said he.</p>
            <p>“Oh no!” cried the sheep “you are so very respectable that it would never do that
               you should mix yourself up in the affairs of a silly sheep, and a beast of
               prey.”</p>
            <p>The Haymaker insisted that she listen to him, and be guided by him.</p>
            <p>“But I know myself what is best for me,” cried the sheep. “Let me go away off to
               some quiet place where I can be quite alone. There I may be able to recover my
               former tranquility of mind. As it is, I fear I am in too dangerous a state to be
               allowed to roam about freely. It is a dreadful thing to find out that one is a
               ravening sheep. How do I know, or how do you know, to what wild deed my fevered
               mind may prompt me. Suppose I should suddenly spring upon the wild bull, drag
               him to <pb/>the ground, and tear his vitals from his quivering body.</p>
            <p>“That would, indeed, be horrible,” said the Haymaker; “but worse yet than that
               may happen.”</p>
            <p>“Worse than that!” Cried the sheep in an awe-stricken voice.</p>
            <p>“Yes; there is a lower depth still,” and he spoke in a voice as hollow and
               ghastly that a thrill went through the veins of the sheep, and chilled her very
               heart.</p>
            <p>“Suppose the pigs and the grasshoppers should find it out?”</p>
            <p>With a cry of horror the sheep fell swooning upon the ground. She had never
               thought of that. In her ignorance and stupidity she had thought nothing could be
               worse than to know one’s self to be a ravening sheep; but oh heavens! That the
               pigs and the grasshoppers should know!</p>
            <p>Crushed and humiliated she was carried off to a small paddock by the sea; here
               she nibbled grass on the hillside, and trotted by the beach, and might have
               become reasonable, cheerful in her latter days, but for the awful dread that
               always lay like a stone in her heart, “Suppose the pigs and the grasshoppers
               should know.”</p>
            <p>The Haymaker came in time to dislike all thought or mention of the sheep; for he,
               too, was terrified lest the pigs and grasshoppers should know, and it should be
               whispered about that a man as staid and respectable as he had once known a
               ravening sheep.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      
      <back>
         <div type="editorial">
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="narratorB">
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Sheep</persName>
                  <sex value="F"></sex>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>Sheep</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Lamb</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>she-wolf</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <interpGrp type="charActs">
               <interp xml:id="grief">indicating a character's display of grief, sadness, loss.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="fear">indicating a character's display of fear, anger, terror, distress.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="joy">indicating a character's display of joy, happiness.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="unsure">indicating a character's display of uncertainty, mistrust, or confusion.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
            <interpGrp type="genre">
               <interp xml:id="gothic">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the Gothic genre.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="wonder">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the wonder tale genre.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
