<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Four Short Stories: A Digital Edition</title>
            <author>
               <persName>Fanny Van de Grift Stevenson</persName>
            </author>
            <editor> R Pritzker </editor>
            <principal> A Lang </principal>
            <funder> Centre for Data, Culture, and Society: University of Edinburgh </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <ab><!-- unpublished manuscripts with permission of the Robert Louis Stevenson Museum in St. Helena, California--></ab>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>St. Helena, California</settlement>
                  <repository>Robert Louis Stevenson Museum</repository>
                  <idno>Scrapbook 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="ScribeA" scribeRef="FVS">Clear, cursive script</handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>



   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <div hand="#ScribeA">
            <head type="title">Ah Choon and the Sorcerer</head>
            <p> A Chinese fisherman of <placeName>Amoy</placeName> for many days had cast his nets
               only to draw them to land empty. Walking the streets that he might there-by forget in
               some degree the hunger that assailed him, he encountered a figure that arrested his
               attention. It was that of a beggar apparently in the most abject destitution. His
               skin was filthy, and he was clothed in rags; There was a weird strange look in his
               eyes, and a gleam of intelligence at variance with his condition shone through the
               dirt that encrusted his face. Ah Choon, the fisherman, felt that somewhere before he
               had met the beggar when he presented a very different aspect. At last it occurred to
               him that it must be an emperor’s sorcerer, who had probably chosen this disguise that
               he might walk the streets undisturbed by the prayers and solicitations of those who
               believed in his powers.</p>
            <p>This great magician was said to know all things known to man or devils. He could
               foretell deaths, and the rise and fall of empires, so great was his knowledge that
               the spirits of the air had limited him in his prophecies. If he told all he knew
               fierce lightning would burst from the sky and devour him in its fire.</p>
            <p>Ah Choon bowed his head to the ground before the sorcerer and cried “give me
               something I beseech you” Give me something, I beseech you or I will implore you
               forever!”</p>
            <p>“Rise my son,” said the sorcerer, “How can I give you what I have not myself? You see
               I am but a wretched beggar; it is you who must give to me.”</p>
            <p>Ah Choon still besought him until the old man losing patience thrust him on one side.
               As he did so, Ah Choon snatched from his breast a handful of the beggar’s rags and
               ran to cast his nets, throwing into them as he did a scrap of the rags. <pb/> The
               nets came up bursting with fine large fish.</p>
            <p>Ah Choon hied him to the market where he soon disposed of his fish for a good sum and
               went home his pockets heavy with cash.</p>
            <p>The next day he cast his nets again with the same good luck. But when he went to the
               market to sell his fish a jabbering crowd surrounded him. “Cheat! Swindler” They
               cried “Who sold us enchanted fish that were fat and large when we bought them, and
               but empty air when we opened our baskets!”</p>
            <p>The Fisherman turned pale. Here, my friends, he cried. choose from those I have
               caught today, and if the same thing happens again you will help me to find and punish
               the wicked sorcerer who has put a cheat both upon you and me!” And he told his story
               to the gaping crowd.</p>
            <p>When they turned to fill their baskets, no fish were there; only a few fresh leaves.
               Ah Choon felt a chill at his back. Turning he beheld the sorcerer in his beggar’s
               garb. All perceived him at the same moment.</p>
            <p>“Tis he!” They cried, “Tear him to pieces!” And rushed forward to attack him. He
               smiled. “One moment my children.” he said, “and you may do with me as you will. Let
               me amuse you first.” As he said this he spat on the ground a black spittle into which
               he dipped the end of his long finger and drew figures upon a white wall. As he drew
               the figures sprang from under his fingers, writhing over the wall in a hideous
               manner. The gaze of all who waited upon the little friends who leered at the
               spectators changed heads with each other, spread their mouths from ear to ear in
               demonish glee, struck at each other, and contorted their limbs. So frightful an
               exhibition did it finally become that the mob with one accord turned and fled. Some
               of the boldest looking back saw the sorcerer, still serenely smiling, strike the
               figures dead with his staff, wrap with rags about him and melt into a light gray
               cloud, which gradually dissolved into the air. After that time the fisherman’s luck
               was variable, but he tried no more magic arts to increase his gains.</p>
         </div>

      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="editorial">
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="narratorD"> </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Ah Choon</persName>
                  <sex value="M"/>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>humanoid</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Mermaiden</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Sorcerer of the Sea</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <interpGrp type="charActs">
               <interp xml:id="grief">indicating a character's display of grief, sadness,
                  loss.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="fear">indicating a character's display of fear, anger, terror,
                  distress.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="joy">indicating a character's display of joy, happiness.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="unsure">indicating a character's display of uncertainty, mistrust, or
                  confusion.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
            <interpGrp type="genre">
               <interp xml:id="gothic">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the Gothic
                  genre.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="wonder">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the wonder tale
                  genre.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
